in 1943 we see the tide really turns in
favor of the Allies
especially in Europe but it's actually
happening in the pacific as well
to begin with in 1943 the siege of
Stalingrad was doesn't quite exactly fit
on this map it would be would be
right lira right over here it ends
with the soviets being two tours in this
is actually an incredible story there's
many movies about the siege it sounds
stalingrad
for a reason thus the the soviets are
able to mount a ver
pretty epic counterattack by attacking
the flanks
the axes are mean they're able to push
the back in defeat the axes army
stalingrad itself gets reduced to rubble
and you know if you actually look at
pictures up its
its its its kind of mind-blowing to
deceive imagine what went on there
stalingrad right over here although
right now leningrad in 1943 still under
siege in if you want your stomach to
really be sick
look up images of of things that
happened over there
but needless to say 1943 its a turning
or it's not the turning point for you to
really is a turning point but 1943
the moment and really in the allies
favor the soviets be defeat
the germans stalingrad were able to push
the Germans and the Axis powers
out the caucuses and then they can they
begin to advance
and then the soviets begin to advance
and retake
ground from the Axis powers now at the
same time
you might remember that at the end the
in in North Africa in North Africa
let me go rate over you have all these
maps layered over here
you might remember that the British were
able to
push back the axis army back into Libyan
in this case continues as we go into
nineteen
as we go into nineteen forty-three and
the Allied armies essentially able to
kick the axis army
out love North African be victorious in
North African you remember
yeah these the armies that are coming
from Egypt you also had
you also had allies land in Morocco
in algeria and they all meet up
and by mid-year they're able to use
their victory in North Africa
as a launching point to start attacking
the mainland amid Lee the first
they can go to sicily but then they go
to the actual
mainlanders attack at Salerno and a
starter
to really kind of bite their way up the
Italian peninsula
go do this in a blue-collar so you can
see this is
the allies as we go into bid
and late 1943 are able to take more and
more
love the Italian the Italian peninsula
now as this happen as this happens
conditions in Italy aren't good
the Italian people aren't happy and
they're actually able to depose
mussolini
let me write that down so this is in
mousseline E mousseline the
do you think there's another s mussolini
is deposed
moose so the is
mousseline E is deposed as we get later
that year
Italy warmly surrenders to the allies
there with that said italy has
surrendered
but the entire country heavily the
entire type it in so they're still
axis troops there so the allies have to
continue to slog to 1943 1944
and even into nineteen forty-five to
completely rid
Italy love the Axis powers especially
the germans
now role especially is fairly hard
bombing campaign starring role
in order to completely get the Axis
powers I love that and that all is
happening
in 19 this is all happening in nineteen
forty-three now other other things have
noted there's many things that are
happening
in Europe and once again these are just
overview videos
that are happening in 1943 is american
forces
he is early is not early 1943 are able
to start doing
bombing attacks on Germany itself these
bombing attacks
only become more and more fears as the
war progresses
another battle at No %uh
note in made 1943 is the battle love
cursed
Kirk's and this is really the last
offensive
that the Axis powers are able to mount
on the Eastern Front
and their defeated in this battle by the
soviets
and then once again that allows the
soviets to start going on
the offensive so when you look at things
from a European point of view
the allies are definitely they have the
ball cover the momentum now there now
what kind of putting the squeeze on the
Axis powers
and frankly the same thing is happening
in the Pacific
the especially the americans there now
on the offensive able to get closer and
closer and closer
to Japan